<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
    <!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>


<!--
<!ENTITY I-D.homma-slice-provision-models PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.homma-slice-provision-models.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.nsdt-teas-ietf-network-slice-definition PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.nsdt-teas-ietf-network-slice-definition.xml'>
-->


<!ENTITY I-D.contreras-teas-slice-nbi PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.contreras-teas-slice-nbi.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.irtf-nmrg-ibn-concepts-definitions PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.irtf-nmrg-ibn-concepts-definitions.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices.xml'>



<!--
    <!ENTITY rfc8456 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8456.xml'>


<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-network-programming PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-spring-srv6-network-programming.xml'>
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-detnet-architecture PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-detnet-architecture.xml'>
-->

<!--
     <!ENTITY rfc4605 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4605.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc5798 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5798.xml'>
    <!ENTITY rfc7287 PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7287.xml'>

<!ENTITY I-D.haleplidis-sdnrg-layer-terminology PUBLIC ''
      'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.haleplidis-sdnrg-layer-terminology.xml'>
-->
]>


<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="5"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-contreras-nmrg-transport-slice-intent-05"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
      <title abbrev="IETF Network Slice Intent">
      IETF Network Slice Intent</title>

    <!-- AUTHORS -->
    <author fullname="Luis M. Contreras"
            initials="LM."
            surname="Contreras">
      <organization abbrev="Telefonica">
        Telefonica
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Ronda de la Comunicacion, s/n</street>
          <street>Sur-3 building, 3rd floor</street>
          <city>Madrid</city>
          <code>28050</code>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <email>luismiguel.contrerasmurillo@telefonica.com</email>
         <uri>http://lmcontreras.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Panagiotis Demestichas"
            initials="P."
            surname="Demestichas">
      <organization abbrev="WINGS">
        WINGS ICT Solutions
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street> </street>
          <city> </city>
          <code> </code>
          <country>Greece</country>
        </postal>
        <email>pdemest@wings-ict-solutions.eu</email>
       </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jeff Tantsura"
            initials="J."
            surname="Tantsura">
      <organization abbrev="Microsoft">
        Microsoft
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>jefftant.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date month="January" year="2022" />

    <area>Internet</area>

    <workgroup>NMRG</workgroup>

    <abstract>

    <t>
Slicing at the transport network is expected to be offered as part of end-to-end network slices, fostered by the 
introduction of new services such as 5G. This document explores the usage of intent technologies for requesting 
IETF network slices.
   </t>

    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

<!-- 1. Introduction -->
    <section anchor="sec:introduction" title="Introduction">

    <t>
Network slicing is emerging as the future model for service offering in telecom operator networks. 
Conceptually, network slicing provides a customer with an apparent dedicated network built on top 
of logical (i.e. virtual) and/or physical functions and resources supported by a shared infrastructure, 
provided by one or more telecom operators.
   </t>

    <t>
The concept of network slicing has been largely fostered by the advent of 5G services that are 
expected to be deployed on top of different kind of slices, each built to support specific characteristics 
(extreme low latency, high bandwidth, etc).
    </t>

    <t>
As part of an end-to-end network slice it is expected to have a number of network slices at transport level (referred as IETF network slices)  
providing the necessary connectivity to the rest of components of the end-to-end slice, e.g., mobile 
packet core slice.
    </t>

    <t>
For a definition of an IETF network slice refer to <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices" />. The following paragraph is directly taken from it: 
“An IETF Network Slice Service enables connectivity between a set of CEs with specific Service Level Objectives (SLOs) and Service Level Expectations (SLEs) 
over a common underlay network.”
    </t>
<t>
Intent is a high-level, declarative goal that operates at the level of a network and services it provides, not individual devices.
It is used to define outcomes and high-level operational goals.
</t>
    <t>
In consequence, it seems very convenient to apply the intent-based mechanisms for the provision of IETF 
network slices, providing the adequate level of abstraction towards the transport network control and management 
planes.
    </t>

    <t>
This document leverages current industry trends in the definition of end-to-end 
network slices. The final objective is to describe intents that can be used to flexibly declare the operational aspects and goals 
of an IETF network slice, meaning that the customer could declare what kind of IETF network slice is needed (the outcome) and 
not how to achieve the goals of the IETF network slice.
    </t>

    </section>
<!-- end Introduction -->


<!--
      <t>
        <list style="hanging">
         <t hangText="Upstream interface:">
   A proxy device's interface in the direction of the root of the
   tree. Also called the "Host interface".
	</t>
         <t hangText="Downstream interface:">
   Each of a proxy device's interfaces that is not in the direction
   of the root of the tree. Also called the "Router interfaces".
	</t>
        </list>
      </t>
-->


<!-- Section 2. Transport slice intent -->

<section title="IETF network slice intent">

    <t>
As stated in <xref target="I-D.irtf-nmrg-ibn-concepts-definitions" />, "Intent is a declaration of operational goals 
   that a network is supposed to meet and outcomes that the
   network is supposed to deliver, without specifying how to achieve or
   how to implement them.  Those goals and outcomes are defined in a
   manner that is purely declarative - they specify what to accomplish,
   not how to achieve it."
   </t>

    <t>
When applied to transport networks, this implies that an intent for IETF network slices should provide the necessary 
abstraction with respect to implementation details, including the final devices (or resources) involved, and be 
focused on the characteristics and performance expectations related to it.
   </t>

   <t>
With that aim it can be expected that the intent based system can fulfill and assure the requested IETF 
network slice, triggering initial configurations at the time of initial provisioning and corrective actions during the 
IETF network slice lifetime.
   </t>

   <t>
Regarding the corrective actions it is possible to differentiate two levels. First, corrective actions that could be performed by 
the management and control capabilities of the network (i.e., by the IETF Network Slice Controller) to maintain the Service level Objectives 
(SLOs) as originally declared in the slice intent, so being these internal actions to the management and control elements of the network. 
Second, corrective actions that could be necessary to perform due to incongruences between the SLOs expressed in the intent and the observed 
monitoring information, then requiring some adaptation to the intent itself in order to perform the corrective action. 
   </t>
  
</section>

<!-- End of Section 2. Transport slice intent -->



<!-- Section 3. Foundation of transport slice intents -->

<section title="Foundation of IETF network slice intents">

    <t>
The industrial interest around 5G is accelerating network deployments and operational changes.
   </t>

   <t>
With this respect, the GSMA has been developing a universal blueprint that can be used by any vertical 
customer to request the deployment of a network slice instance (NSI) based on a specific set of service 
requirements.  Such a blueprint is a network slice descriptor called Generic Slice Template (GST) <xref target="GSMA" />.  
The GST contains multiple attributes that can be used to characterize a network slice.  A particular 
template filled with values generates a specific Network Slice Type(NEST).
   </t>

   <t>
Such templates refer to the end-to-end network slice, including the transport part. Despite the fact that some 
of the values would not have applicability for the transport network, others do. An analysis of the relevant 
attributes is performed in <xref target="I-D.contreras-teas-slice-nbi" />.
   </t>

   <t>
According to 3GPP propositions <xref target="TS28.541" />, an upper 3GPP Management System interacts with the transport 
network for establishing the necessary slices at the transport level. Such interaction can be expected 
to happen using the IETF network slice intent, described to an intent-based system (IBS) in the transport 
network part. Then, according to the intent lifecycle in <xref target="I-D.irtf-nmrg-ibn-concepts-definitions" />, the IBS, after recognizing the intent, will proceed 
to translate it in order to interact with a IETF network slice controller by using a NBI as proposed in <xref target="I-D.contreras-teas-slice-nbi" />.
   </t>
  
   <t>
<xref target="fulfillment"/> captures the intent procedure for the fulfillment phase (assurance phase will be detailed in future versions of this draft).
   </t>
  
	<figure anchor="fulfillment" align="center" title="Fulfillment phase of the Transport Slicing Intent">
          <artwork align="left">
          <![CDATA[

          User Space   :       Translation / IBS       :  Network Ops
                       :            Space              :     Space
                       :                               :
         +----------+  :  +----------+   +-----------+ : +-----------+
 Fulfill |recognize/|---> |translate/|-->|  learn/   |-->| configure/|
         |generate  |     |          |   |  plan/    |   | provision |
         |intent    |<--- |  refine  |   |  render   | : |           |
         +----------+  :  +----------+   +-----------+ : +-----------+
                       :                               :
 .........................................................................

     Slice Customer    :                   Slice Provider
     --------------    :                   --------------
                       :
    - Customized Slice :  - Identification of IETF     : - Slice request
      Templates        :    network slice endpoints    :   to IETF NSC by
    - Service SLOs as  :    and connectivity pattern   :   using slice
      understood by    :  - Derivation of network SLOs :   NBI YANG model 
      slice customer   :    and SLEs from high-level   :
                       :    Customer Service SLOs      :
                       :                               :
]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>

</section>

<!-- End of Section 3. Foundation of transport slice intents -->


<!-- Section 4. Mechanisms for translating transport slice intents -->

<section title="Mechanisms for translating IETF network slice intents">

    <t>
This section describes approaches for implementing mechanisms to translate IETF network slice intents. As part of such translation it could be necessary to translate
the slice needs expressed by the customer in terms of service-specific SLOs (e.g., high-resolution real-time video quality) to network- or connectivity-specific SLOs 
(e.g., a correspondent throughput and/or latency) which are the SLOs an IETF Network Slice Controller understands. More on this can be found in <xref target="TMV" />.
   </t>


<!-- Section 4.1. Translation approaches and interaction with the upper systems -->
<section title="Translation approaches and interaction with the upper systems">

    <t>
A suite of mechanisms will be required to allow instantiation of the user’s intent into a IETF network slice. 
In order to be able to deliver an end2end Intent driven slice - a well defined set of context aware attributes that allow unambiguous instantiation of the intent should be agreed upon.
A combination of a structured set of attributes communicated between an IBN and an upper layer system with user input would allow an IBN to have intent modeled and reason about its completeness/validity.
Translation approaches and interaction with the upper systems might benefit from Natural Language Processing (NLP) technics that are needed for enabling high level expression of requirements found missing.

The goal would be to identify and classify the answers for as many fields as possible from the Generic Slice Template (GST), based on the free text / speech 
provided by the user. As it is highly unlikely that the minimum set of fields to properly define an IETF network slice (geo-temporal 
characteristics, performance characteristics, SLO and SLA properties) will be fulfilled in this first step, a follow up two-step approach 
might need to be implemented.
   </t>

      <t>
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>The minimum missing fields from the GST have to be identified and appropriate questions have to be generated 
                  (e.g. based on a pool of available questions correlated with each field, or based on AI approaches).
            </t>

            <t>An iterative interrogation phase will be initiated towards the user using the previously generated questions, 
                  until the user provides all the missing information, so the intent can be modeled accordingly.
            </t>

          </list>
      </t>

      <t>
Interaction with the user and higher-up systems can potentially be further improved by utilizing Machine Learning techniques.
      </t>


</section>
<!-- End of Section 4.1. Translation approaches and interaction with the upper systems -->


<!-- Section 4.2.  Intent-based system suite -->
<section title="Intent-based system suite">

    <t>
In order to consolidate on the set of devices, technologies and resources to be used, a combination of deterministic or stochastic computation approaches will be needed. 
Deterministic approaches will rely on mathematical models and respective algorithms. 
Stochastic approaches will rely on technologies like machine learning. Their goal will be to learn from experience, so as to optimize 
future decisions from the viewpoint of speed and reliability. The target of learning will be related to the service behavior and to the 
anticipated network status in the area and time period of the service provision.
   </t>

</section>
<!-- End of Section 4.2.  Intent-based system suite -->

</section>

<!-- End of Section 4. Mechanisms for translating transport slice intents -->


<!-- Security Considerations -->
     <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

       <t>
To be done.
      </t>

     </section>
<!-- end Security Considerations -->


<!-- IANA Considerations -->
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>
This draft does not include any IANA considerations
      </t>

    </section>
<!-- end IANA Considerations -->


</middle>


<back>

    <references title="References">

     <reference anchor="GSMA">
        <front>
          <title>Generic Network Slice Template, version 5.0</title>
          <author></author>
          <date month="June" year="2021"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="NG.116" value=""/>
      </reference>

     <reference anchor="TMV">
        <front>
          <title>Service performance measurement methods over 5G experimental networks</title>
          <author></author>
          <date month="May" year="2021"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="5G-PPP TMV" value=""/>
      </reference>

      &I-D.contreras-teas-slice-nbi;
      &I-D.irtf-nmrg-ibn-concepts-definitions;
      &I-D.ietf-teas-ietf-network-slices;

     <reference anchor="TS28.541">
        <front>
          <title>TS 28.541 Management and orchestration; 5G Network Resource Model (NRM); Stage 2 and stage 3 (Release 16) V16.2.0.</title>
          <author></author>
          <date month="September" year="2019"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="3GPP TS 28.541 V16.2.0" value=""/>
      </reference>
<!--
      &rfc5798;
      &rfc7287; 
-->
<!--
<xref target="I-D.homma-slice-provision-models" />
-->


      
    </references>

<!-- Acknowledgments -->
    <section numbered="false" anchor="ACK" title="Acknowledgments">

      <t>
This work has been partly funded by the European Commission through the H2020 project 5G-EVE (Grant Agreement no. 815074).
      </t>

    </section>
<!-- end Acknowledgments -->

<!-- Contributors -->
    <section numbered="false" anchor="Contrib" title="Contributors">

      <t>
Kostas Tsagkaris, Kostas Trichias, Vassilis Foteinos, and Thanasis Gkiolias (all from WINGS ICT Solutions) have also contributed to this 
work.

      </t>

    </section>
<!-- end Contributors -->

  </back>
 

</rfc>
